"Dental Implant Overdentures and Cognitive Function"
Systematic reviews
and meta-analyses
have found that tooth loss,
or periodontitis,
is associated with
both cognitive impairment
and dementia.
Reverse causation might be
an intuitive explanation,
dementia leading to a decline
in oral hygiene,
but prospective studies
following people over time
have found that tooth loss
appears to predict
future cognitive decline,
and the more missing teeth,
the higher the associated risk.
Genetic determinants
of elevated periodontitis risk
do not appear
to be associated
with the development
of Alzheimer's disease,
suggesting the association
may be due
to shared
or confounding risk factors.
A poor diet
or low socioeconomic status
represent common pathways for
both tooth loss and dementia,
but even studies controlling
for confounding factors
found a connection
between tooth loss and dementia.
However, one factor that wasn't
controlled for was intelligence.
Those with higher IQ
are both more likely to floss,
and have fewer
tooth and gum problems
as well as have
a delayed onset
of clinically
detectable Alzheimer's
due to
a greater cognitive reserve.
Are there any
potential causal mechanisms
beyond the chronic inflammation?
If you induce periodontitis
in mice with P. gingivalis,
the keystone pathogen
in human periodontitis,
the bacteria
ends up in their brains
and triggers an increase
in the Alzheimer's-associated
plaque protein amyloid beta.
Since then,
evidence of the bacteria
has been found
in human Alzheimer's brains.
Clinical trials
are now underway
to see if blocking
its neurotoxic effects
will have
any therapeutic benefit.
A clue to
a stranger potential mechanism
was unearthed in
a subgroup analysis
of a tooth loss
and dementia meta-analysis.
Only tooth loss
among those without dentures
was associated with the
later development of dementia.
The same tooth loss
with dentures was not.
How does that make any sense?
A review entitled
"Mastication for the Mind"
compiled a number of studies
suggesting that chewing,
mastication in medical speak,
is somehow important
for proper brain function.
For example, the extraction
of teeth from aged mice
appears to upset
their memory and learning.
But maybe they're just upset,
in pain, inflamed,
from having their teeth removed.
A more convincing series
of experiments
compared mice
given food pellets
versus the same pellets
crushed into powder.
Those eating the "soft" diet,
the powdered diet,
also suffered a loss in memory
and learning capacity.
What does chewing
have to do with cognition?
Stick an ultrasound probe
on someone's head
and you can detect an increase
in cerebral blood flow
of the largest artery branch
in the brain
when they clench their jaw
or chew gum.
In an fMRI machine,
brain scans show
enhanced cognitive arousal
when chewing even tasteless,
sugarless gum,
though translational studies
on the acute cognitive effects
of gum chewing
are contradictory.
Maybe it's not the chewing,
though.
Check this out.
Noticing that people
missing molars
on one side of their mouths
have
asymmetrically-sized pupils,
a smaller pupil
on the missing molar side,
researchers tested whether
implanting dental crowns
to replace the missing teeth
could reduce the discrepancy,
and it did.
The study, subtitled "New Teeth
for a Brighter Brain,"
suggested that a gap
in the sensation of teeth
pushing against one another
adversely affects
brain function.
To put it to the test,
we'd want to randomize
people with missing teeth
to get dentures
and see if their cognition
improves over those who don't.
No such studies exist,
but there was an intriguing
pilot study performed.
Ten toothless individuals,
9 out of 10 of them
cognitively impaired,
6 of them severely so,
were given conventional dentures
for a month
before being fitted
with overdentures,
which are snapped
into titanium implants
surgically screwed
into the jawbone.
The conventional dentures,
held in place by adhesives
and natural suction,
did nothing to significantly
alter cognitive function.
But the ones securely attached
to implants in the bone,
presumably transmitting
the same kind
of chewing pressure sensations
to the nerves in the jaw
that natural roots
of teeth might,
had a dramatic effect.
Nine out of ten
of the subjects
went into the study
cognitively impaired,
but 8 out of 10 left the study
cognitively intact.
This suggests well-fitting,
secure dental prosthesis
isn't just about improving
self-confidence,
social contact,
quality of life,
but proper brain functioning
as well.
Of course, even better, though,
would be to preserve
the teeth you have.